The Unmovable Sovereign, Ozen the Immovable.
「不動卿」動かざるオーゼン
This irredeemable lesson of hers
is a trial before setting off anew...
その度し難いレッスンは新たなる旅立ちへの試練
It is "survival training" to help these children stay alive
as they make their way through the world of the Abyss.
アビス世界で子供達が生き抜いてゆくための「生存訓練」
Spend ten days here with the equipment you've got.
Show me you're able to survive.
その装備で十日間 生き延びてみせな
Be sure not to go beyond that Pillar Tree.
あの「柱の木」から向こうへはいかないように
I'll consider that as trying to escape.
逃げたとみなすからね
Well then, I'm heading back now.
それじゃ 私は帰るよ
Huh?!
Do your best to protect this girl
so that she doesn't return to being a corpse.
この子を死体に戻さないよう せいぜい守ってやるんだね
In addition, you can't use that thing for these ten days.
それと
そいつを10日間 使うのはなしだ
火葬砲を
My Incinerator?
Go ahead and use it if you want to get Riko killed.
リコを死なせたいなら 使ってもいいよ
どういうこと
What do you mean?
Once you fire it, no matter how you push yourself,
you always faint after around ten minutes.
撃ったが最後
君はどんなに気張っても10分程度で昏倒
Then it's a full two hours until you wake up.
目覚めるまで たっぷり二時間かかる
Just try leaving a helpless child on her own
in the second layer for two hours.
深層で二時間無力な子供を放置して見なよ
I wonder just how she'll be torn to shreds and eaten...
どんな風に食い散らかされるかねえ
Still, when you really do have to use it,
ま それでおまえやらなきゃいけない時は
go all out to make sure whatever it is
doesn't come after you again in the future.
後腐れが残らないように徹底てきになるんだね
No matter your opponent or whatever lies in the vicinity,
相手が誰であろうと周りに何があろうと
when the time comes, don't hesitate or show any mercy.
その時が来たら躡躇も容赦も無しだ
Otherwise, your adventure will be over
in the blink of an eye.
さもなきゃ 君らの冒険が終わるのなんて あっという間さ
Daremo ga sakaraezu ni mogutteiku
誰もが逆らえずに潜っていく
その目を灯火より輝かせて
Sono me o tomoshibi yori kagayakasete
Mezasu saki wa fukaku
目指す先は深く まっすぐに迷い込む
Massugu ni mayoikomu
Kuchiaketa naraku no wana
口開けた奈落の罠 真実の跡を追いかけよう
Shinjitsu no ato o oikakeyou
Ima kotae ga mitsukaru nara zenbu nakushitemo ii
今答えが 見つかるなら 全部失くしてもいい
Sono koe o hanasanai youni kodama ga mada hibiiteru
その声を 離さないように 木霊がまだ響いてる
羅針盤はずっと 闇を指したまま逃げ場のない 方へ
Rashinban wa zutto
Yami o sashita mama
Nigeba no nai
Hou e
Sore ga noroi demo
それが呪いでも 鼓動は本物
Kodou wa honmono
二度と憧れは 止まらない
Nidoto akogare wa tomaranai
Survival Training
First of all, we need to look for some water...
まずは水を探さないとね
Ah, what's that?
何あれ
It's glowing!
光ってるよ
A-ah, Riko, be careful!
リコ気をつけて
Wow!
How beautiful!
綺麗
This is great. We found some water!
よかったね 水があったよ
Think it's okay to drink?
飲めるのか
It's fine!
大丈夫
Those are rohanas,
a kind of insect that only lives in clean water.
あれは ロオハナっていって 綺麗な水しか住まない虫なの
Ah...!
Hm?
Damn...
くそ あれのどこが大人しいんだ
In what way is that thing docile?
We did it!
やった
Around here, the animals have regressed eyes,
so they should be susceptible to light.
この辺りの動物 目が退化してるから 光に弱いはずだよ
If we build a fire, I think they'll keep their distance.
火を焚いてれば 近寄ってこないと思うんだ
"Susceptible to light," huh?
光に弱いのでは
Let's go look for some insect-repelling plants...
虫除けの草 探そうか
Day 3
How's it looking?
どうだい
Riko is certainly plucky,
リコちゃんは肝は据わってるけど
but her body can't keep up with what she wants to do...
やりたいことが身体がついて行ってないの
レグ少年もなぁ
And that boy Reg...
身体はめっぽう打たれ強いが
Although his body is extraordinarily resilient,
he's constantly losing his nerves...
Riko, where are you?
Although his body is extraordinarily resilient,
he's constantly losing his nerves...
しょっちゅうビビるし
and is slow to make decisions.
判断が遅いの
Stop it!
This despite the fact he's a mechanical doll...
機械人形なのにの
I see...
そうかい
You're not going out there?
行ってやらんのか
If they die now, it just means
they didn't have what it takes to go any further.
あれで死んだら そこまでだったていう話さ
Day 5
Reg, you're strong, but your body is light...
レグは強いけど 身体が軽いからね
So we'll have to devise a plan
if we're going to catch that hippo thing...
あのカバ捕まえるには 工夫しないと
In that case, maybe I could extend my arm
to bind it to a tree or something...
ならば腕をのばして 樹に縛り付けてしまうとか
Uh-huh, uh-huh...
じゃあ誘導しよ
Well, then let's lead it there!
How?
どうやって
Ta-da!
We'll use this!
これ使お
What the heck is it? It stinks...
なんだこれ
臭い
It's dung from a female and some tree bark.
I tore off a piece that's covered in pheromones.
メスのうんちと樹の皮 フェロモンがついてるとこ剥がしてきたの
Use this to lure it.
これで おびき寄せて
And when it gets close to you, Reg,
we'll blind it with our glow-stones!
レグのところまで来たら 石灯で目くらまし
How's that sound?!
どう
H-hmm...
うまくいくだろうか
You think it will work?
It'll be fine! Let's just try our best!
大丈夫 頑張ろう
Do it now! Reg!
今よ レグ
Be it an immature body or weak psyche,
幼い身体も弱い心も そうすぐには変わらんが
they won't be showing real changes
in those areas any time soon...
But, just as you predicted, they're making
enormous progress in the things they're good at.
あんたの言う通り
あの子ら得意なことは すこぶる伸びがいいのう
Well, there are two of them, after all...
ま せっかく二人いるんだしの
So it's best that they learn to depend on one another.
互いに背中をあずけられるようになればええの
"Depend on one another," huh?
背中を預けるねぇ
Ozen!
オーゼン オーゼン
Who attacked you?!
誰にやられた
Just you wait! I'll annihilate those punks!
待ってろ 連中を根絶やしにしてやる
What's the matter, Ozen?
どうしたオーゼン もう降参か
You giving up already?
This is amazing, Ozen!
A whole field of Flowers of Fortitude!
すごいぞ オーゼン
一面「不屈の花」だ
It doesn't even feel like we're in the middle
of the netherworld!
奈落のただ中とは思えないな
This is Torka from my squad.
うちの隊のトーカだ
こいつと結婚したぞ
I got married to him!
Sorry, Ozen...
すまないオーゼン
少し 一人にさせてくれないか
Do you mind giving me a bit of time alone?
How incredibly maddening.
本当に忌々しい
To think that no sooner than
Torka quickly passed away...
トーカがさっさと逝ったと思ったら
even the baby was stillborn...
赤子まで死んで出てくるとはね
That's some nerve to leave the delivery to me...
私に取り上げさせといて まったくいい度胸だよ
That dumb face and you come along, and just when Lyza
had finally mellowed out, she gets treated like this?
あの間抜け面とおまえが来て
ただでさえ丸くなったライザにはこの仕打ちかい
How maddening...
忌々しい
I didn't want to see Lyza in such a state.
あんなライザは見たかなったよ
I don't have much strength left.
体力も少ない コイツは ここに置いて
Perhaps I'll just leave this thing behind here
and carry the Bell up with Lyza...
ライザと「鐘」を抱えて登るか
Good grief, I've taken on another burden now...
まったく 厄介事を引き受けたもんだ
Just relax...
安心しろ 私は義理堅いのさ
I have a strong sense of duty.
This is pretty good!
なかなかいけるな
With this we should be able to make it through
the remaining five days!
これで あと五日は乗り切れるね
Yeah.
After 10 Days
大丈夫ですか リコさん
Are you alright, Riko?
Yeah...
Somehow... it feels like ages since we were here...
なんだか 久しぶりに戻った気がする
It's actually been 10 days.
実際十日ぶりですよ
Good work out there.
お疲れ様です お二人ともすごいですね
Both of you are quite amazing.
Personally, I started crying right away...
ぼくなんて すぐ泣いちゃって
Any further out than the Seeker Camp
and it's almost completely dark...
監視基地より奥ってほとんど真っ暗だし
and Master left and went back home by herself
somewhere along the way...
お師様だけ 途中で帰っちゃうし
Marulk, you know, even I...
マルルク 僕だってその
Near the end when I got separated from Riko,
I was feeling so hopeless...
リコと引き離された最後の方は
あまりに心細くて
ほんとですか
Really?!
Absolutely.
そりゃもう
Reg, so that happens to even you, huh?
レグさんでもそうなっちゃうんですね
That makes me feel a bit better.
ちょっと安心しました
Are you hungry? I'll bring you something to eat!
お腹すいてません
何か持ってきます
So it's already been ten days, huh?
もう十日も経つのか
Now that I think about it, the pain I was feeling
from Ozen's thrashing is gone now.
オーゼンにやられた痛みも 気付けばもうないな
I wonder if the "Riko Hodgepodge Stew" did the trick...
「リコ闇鍋」が効いたのかな
Alright!
よし 修復完了だ
My rehabilitation is complete!
This pattern...
この模様 こんな形だったっけ
Was it always like that...?
What does it mean, anyway?
何だろうなこれ
At any rate...
それにしても 一向に筋肉がつかないな
seems I never put on any muscle...
Reg! Riko!
レグさん リコさん
お師様が戻ってきたのなら食事にしようと言ってます
Master is saying that now that you're back,
we should all have a meal.
Food!
ごはん
So how was it?
どうだったかね 十日間過ごしてみて
Spending 10 days there, I mean.
It was pretty hectic, wasn't it?
結構 忙しかったよね
That's right...
そうだな 過ぎてみればあっという間だったような
Looking back at it now,
it feels like it was over in the blink of an eye.
"Don't stay in the deep layers
if you don't want to kill those who're waiting for you"...
「待ち人を殺したくなければ深層には留まるな」
There's an old saying like that, you see.
なんて古い言い伝えがあってね
どういう意味なんだ
What does it mean?
時間の感覚が狂っちまうんだ
One's sense of time goes mad.
It's particularly striking in the depths of the fifth layer.
五層の深部で特に顕著なんだかがね
I had intended to stay down there a few weeks,
数週間過ごしたつもりが 地上に戻ってきたら数ヶ月も経っていた
but when I returned to the surface,
a few months had passed.
Such occurrences are common...
なんてことがよくあるんだ
So that rumor...
その噂 本当だったんですね
is true, then!
It's no rumor. I'm telling you flat out.
噂なもんかい 私が言ってるんだよ
Well, only those with strange tastes -
まぁ 深層で生活しようなんて物好きは
basically just us White Whistles -
would try living in the deep layers.
私ら白笛ぐらいなもんだかね
That saying I mentioned that
if you stay there for a really long time,
さっきの言い伝えは あまりに長くとどまると
everyone who's waiting for you will probably die,
is somewhat of an exaggeration.
待ち人が皆死んじまうんじゃないかって
大げさに言ったものなのさ
Still, you probably think it has nothing to do with you
since you're making a journey of no return...
戻らぬ旅の君らには関係ない話に思えるだろうけど
But the problem is that
we can't even estimate the extent
問題は六層 七層では
この「狂い」がどの程度になるのか見当も付かないって事さ
to which this "madness" manifests
in the sixth and seventh layers.
I have a feeling that perhaps not as much time
as we all think has actually passed for Lyza.
ライザは 我々が思ってる程 時を過ごしてはいないんじゃないのかね
Ten years on the surface...
地上では十年
But if we assume that only a few years have passed
at the bottom of the netherworld,
だが奈落の底では数年しか経ってないとすれば
don't you get the feeling there's a very good chance
she's alive and well?
彼女が無事である可能性は よっぽど高い気がしないかい
Ozen...
オーゼンさん オーゼンさん
Ozen!
Well, even so, you should do your best
not to stay in the fifth layer for long.
ま それでもなるべく五層には留まらないことだ
And why would that be?
それはなぜだい
So that you don't bump into
any of the other White Whistles...
他の白笛と鉢合わせないようにするためさ
The depths' fifth layer, the Sea of Corpses,
is as deep as humans can go and return alive.
深界五層「亡骸の海」は 人が生きて戻れる限界の深さだ
I suppose some of them are there...
連中の何人かはそこにいるだろうね
The Sovereign of Guidance, Wakuna the Chosen.
「先導卿」選ばれしワクナ
The Sovereign of Mystery, Srajo the Mysterious.
「神秘卿」神秘のスラージョ
「黎明卿」新しきボンドルド
The Sovereign of Dawn, Bondrewd the Novel.
Those are the other three
who are down in the Abyss now.
今潜ってるのはこの3人だ
Among them... Bondrewd in particular
is an out-and-out scoundrel.
連中 特にボンドルドは筋金入りのろくでなしだ
He's not kind like I am, so you better be careful...
私みたいに優しくないから気をつけるんだね
Is that... a joke?
それは冗談なのか
レグ 大丈夫
Reg, you okay?
Ah, that's right...
Speaking of Lyza, I also have something
I'm curious about...
ライザといえばさ 私も気になってるんだけど
The slip in the sealed letter that said:
"At the netherworld's bottom, I'll be waiting"...
封書に入ってた「奈落の底で待つ」
I wonder who wrote that...
あれは誰が書いたんだろうね
Huh?
It's written overly large in crooked penmanship,
略字もなしの古い奈落文字
using old nether glyphs
without any of the simplified forms.
やけに大きく書かれた歪な筆跡
On top of that, the paper it's on isn't even paper.
それに使われてる紙も紙じゃない
It's an unknown Relic.
未知の遺物さ
It looks all worn out, but it really surprised me...
ボロボロのように見えるけど 驚いたよ
That thing can't be ripped even with my strength.
それ 私の力でも破れないんだ
What in the world is waiting down
at the netherworld's bottom together with Lyza?
一体 奈落の底でライザとともに待ってるものはなんだろうね
Well then...
さて 二人ともついてきな
both of you, follow me.
Here.
ほれっ
What's that?
これは
Blaze Reap... the everlasting pickax.
ブレイズリーブ 「無尽鎚」
That's right...
その通り
It's a specialized weapon with which
Lyza the Annihilator spilled much blood.
「殲滅のライザ」が数多の血を吸わせた得物
It was stuck in the ground like a grave marker
in that cluster of Eternal Fortunes I spoke of.
例のトコシエコウの群生地に墓標みたいに刺さってたのさ
Huh?!
お母さんの
My mother's...
Riko...
リコ
中の「尽きない火薬」は無事だが外側がいかれちまってる
The everlasting gunpowder inside it is fine,
but the outer casing is in bad shape.
使えてあと数回さね
It can only be used a few more times at best.
Well, it's a piece of junk
that occasionally misfired even back then.
ま 昔からたまに不発なポンコツだったよ
We're talking about Lyza here,
so I bet she's already found a new weapon.
ライザの事だから 新しい武器ぐらい見つけているだろう
I'll teach you how to use it.
使い方を教えてやるよ
It should be able to act as an alternative
to that Incinerator of yours.
火葬砲の代わりくらいにはなるだろう
You really mean that?!
本当ですか
Thank you!
ありがとうございます
In addition...
それと
What I'm about to tell you
must not be shared with anyone else.
これから話すことは口外無用だ
With those words, Ozen spoke of...
そう言って オーゼンが語ったのは
the numerous secrets that had been transmitted from
the last dives of many generations of White Whistles,
歴代白笛のラストダイヴから漏れ伝えられ
彼らの間だけで口伝されているという 秘密の数々
which are passed down by word of mouth
among only themselves.
恐らくは人が持ち得る最も深いアビスの声だった
Perhaps, those were the very deepest voices of Abyss
that people are capable of carrying to us.
We heard about the cryptic device
for traversing the fifth layer's "Sea"...
深界五層の「海」を超えるための謎めいた仕掛けのこと
About how a white whistle's timbre acts as a key
to activate a certain class of Relics.
「白笛」の音色はある種の遺物を起動する鍵であること
About the mysterious ring of the seventh layer
that only a few White Whistles are said to have seen.
何人かの白笛が見たという深界七層の不思議な輪のこと
子供騙しは嫌いと言ったオーゼンの言葉は本当で
When Ozen said she hates deceiving children,
she was telling the truth...
From start to finish,
this monster sitting before us held nothing back.
この怪物は最初から最後まで 出し惜しみをしなかった
So you're already heading out, huh?
もう 行っちまうのか
It'll be lonely around here.
寂しくなるの
Don't you think it's cold of Ozen not to come see you off?
見送りに来ないなんてオーゼンさんも冷たいんじゃないん
No, it's alright.
いいえ いいんです
Huh?
もういっぱいもらっちゃったから
She's already given us so much, after all...
She's taught us many things...
いろんなこと教えてもらったし
It wouldn't be right to ask any more of her.
これ以上もらったら大変です
What's this?
なんだ
見た目に似合わず慎ましいじゃん
Despite all appearances, you're quite humble.
Hey, cut that out.
おい やめとけ
Marulk!
マルルクちゃん
Well, you take care now.
じゃあ 元気でね
I find it hard to say this, but...
僕 こんな事言うの嫌なんですが
If you come back and say, "It's impossible, after all,"
it'd be oh so nice...
「やっぱり無理だっ」って帰ってきてくれたら どんなにいいかって
マルルク
Marulk...
I've seen off all kinds of people
who leave on journeys they won't return from...
いろんな人が ここから「戻らない旅」に行くのを送ってきました
But... today is the saddest I've ever felt.
僕 今日が一番悲しいです
Reg and that girl...
レグ あの子
As expected, they were quick
to pick up on cave-raiding techniques.
やはり探窟の技術は飲み込みが早かったね
色々思い出すまで行かせたくはなかったなぁ
Although, I didn't want to let them go
until more memories come back...
Well, nothing I can do about it.
ま 仕方ないか
Right, Lyza?
なぁライザ
That baby crawled toward the Abyss
the moment she was let out of the Vessel,
あの赤子 籠からだした途端
アビスの方へ這っていくなんて 気味が悪いったらなかったね
which is pretty darn creepy, right?
Thanks to you, she's monstrously energetic now.
お陰様で元気さは まるきり怪物だ
My apprentice is already fed up with her.
私の弟子もうんざりしていた
Well, that's just splendid...
四そいつは結構なことで
弟子なんていたのかい
You have an apprentice?
His name's Jiruo. You've met him before, right?
ジルオだ 会ったことあるだろ
Ah, that rash and shameless kid
who turned down my invitation...
ああ 私の誘いを断った やたら図太いあの子か
俺は 殲滅卿の方がいいんで
I prefer the Sovereign of Annihilation.
The fact that she hasn't dropped dead or been killed
means you're doing a good job keeping her hidden.
未だにくたばっても殺されてもないってことは
あの子が上手く隠し通せているようだね
If it ever came to light that she's your daughter,
おまえさんの娘だと割れたら
she'd be kidnapped by ruffians
while you're down in the Abyss.
潜ってる隙にならず者に攫われて
And, if you're lucky, she'd be held hostage,
but if you're unlucky...
良くて人質 悪けりゃあ
大丈夫 私の弟子は優秀なんだ
It's alright. My apprentice is top grade.
However, be that as it may...
ただ ただな
Riko is incredibly precious to me.
リコは私にとって余りにも大事なんだ
No matter the Relic or whatever else of mine
I offer as payment, it's not enough.
どんな遺物でも私の何もかもを払っても足りない
Thanks to a whole heap of priceless things,
that girl is alive right now.
尊いものの積み重ねが 今のあの子を生かしている
If I continue to stay with her, I'm liable to take
Riko's right to set off on adventures away from her,
このまま一緒にいたら
私はリコから冒険に挑む権利を奪い
and I myself will likely become separated from the Abyss.
そして私もアビスから離れてしまうだろ
Before that happens, I'm heading out...
そうなる前に 私は行くよ
So that my girl is free to choose whatever path...
あの子がどんな道も選べるように
I wonder what you're glossing over here...
何を取り繕っているのかねぇ
Isn't it true that you simply
got an urge to see the bottom?
「底」を見たくなっただけだろ
なぁ オーゼン
Hey, Ozen...
If Riko once again sets out to reach the bottom
and in doing so comes to stand before you,
再びリコが地の底を目指して あんたの前に立ったら
I'd like you to tell her.
教えてやって欲しい
You mean about how she's a living corpse?
自分が動く死体かも ってことかね
そうだ
That's right.
About how much of a miracle it took
to make it so that she's able to move at all...
どれだけの奇跡が君を動かしてきたのかって事と
About how to tackle the magnificent adventures
that are waiting for her...
その先で待つ素晴らしい冒険への挑み方を
What a pain. Do that yourself.
面倒だね 自分でやりな
Well, if we're just talking about
sending her on to you...
ま お前さんのとこに送り出すぐらいなら
I'll do it.
やってやるさ
Good grief... How irredeemable...
まったく 度し難い
How very irredeemable...
度し難いねぇ
The Inverted Forest... It's so far above us...
逆さ森 あんな上に
Reg...
レグ
Are you ready?
準備はいい
Of course.
もちろんだ
The Depths' Third Layer
Great Fault
Sora ni ukanderu hikaru nami o
空に浮かんでる光る波を束ねて虹の橋をかけよう
Tabanete niji no hashi o kakeyou
Ayaui ashiba, suberu slope
危うい足場 滑るスロープ
Kako to mirai no michishirube
過去と未来の道標
君の左手 僕の右手を
Kimi no hidarite, boku no migite o
Tsunaide tsunagete hajimeyou
繫いで繫げてはじめよう
いつも そばに いるよ
Itsumo soba ni iru yo
過去も 今も 未来も
Kako mo ima mo mirai mo
Dakara mayowazu ni aruiteikou
だから迷わずに歩いていこう
Irotoridori no yume kasanete
色とりどりの夢 重ねて
Ashita wa doko ni mukau
明日はどこに向かう
Kimi to issho ni iretara, sekai wa kagayakidasu yo
君と一緒にいれたら 世界は輝きだすよ
Saihate no chi ni saku hana o sagasou
最果ての地に咲く花を探そう
Next Episode
The Great Fault